Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5552
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records
1967-1972
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Railway Labor Executives' Association (RLEA)
5552
29 cubic feet
29 linear ft.
Records (documents), photographs, newspaper clippings.
This collection consists of the general and office files of the Railway Labor Executives' Association for the years 1968-1972.
5664255
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Elizabeth Parker, January 24, 2018
EAD encoding:
Elizabeth Parker, January 24, 2018
Biographical / Historical
The RLEA was founded in 1926 in response to the passage of the Railway Labor Act. Prior to 1926, there had been an informal association between the railroad labor organizations so that the various chief executives of the different unions could work together to form a unified course of action that would benefit all of their members. This group became more formalized immediately after the end of WW1. The U.S. railroads had been nationalized as part of the war effort, and the railroad labor organizations wanted them to remain under federal management, both because of increased productivity and because of better labor relations with the industry. The effort was ultimately unsuccessful, and the railroads returned to private industry; however, the railroad labor organizations had realized the need to have a united front to counter the carriers and industry groups and lobbyists.
On May 18, 1926, the chief executives of the railroad labor organization met in Washington D.C., formalized their association with By-Laws, and elected officers to serve the newly created RLEA. The original purpose, codified in the original preamble, was co-operative action to obtain and develop consistent interpretations and utilization of the Railway Labor Act. The RLEA was comprised of the chief executives of the 21 railroad labor unions, including the president of the Railway Employees' Department of the AFL, and each member got one vote, regardless of the size of their union. The organization was voluntary, so no member organization was bound by its decisions. Over the course of its existence, various member organizations withdrew and then re-affiliated with the RLEA.
From 1926 to 1938, the RLEA did not maintain an office, but the amount of work and its importance led the RLEA to open an office in Washington DC and employ a full-time Executive Secretary-Treasurer to run it. The RLEA did not engage in collective bargaining itself, but rather lobbied on behalf of its member organizations, securing such achievements as the Railroad Retirement Act and limiting unemployment for its members during the Great Depression. The RLEA's various areas of interest, such as retirement, safety, legal matters, were broken down into committees, each of which reported back to the executive board on the steps being taken in those areas.
Post WW2, the RLEA played a central role in the Marshall Plan, working with non-Communist labor organizations in Western Europe to establish labor policy and also assist in the work of rebuilding the European railroads. The RLEA was also a major factor in international labor union federations, and its decision to affiliate with the International Transport Workers' Federation (ITWF) and to encourage the ITWF not to join with the Soviet affiliated World Federation of Trade Unions was seen as a major victory for the west.
The RLEA, like its member organizations, did not allow African-American members. As such, it was only representing the interests of white railroad employees; black railroad employees were forced, for the most part, to work without recognized union protection. The exception to this was the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters (BSCP), who in 1948 began a series of successful legal challenges to the jurisdictions over various classes of work. As BSCP's successes in the courts mounted up, and the RLEA's member unions and the RLEA itself were being sued for discriminatory practices, the RLEA finally capitulated in 1950, and accepted the BSCP as a member organization.
In 1950, the RLEA joined with the AFL, CIO, and International Association of Machinists to form the United Labor Policy Committee. This committee oversaw the labor representatives of the Wage Stabilization Board.
In the latter half of the 20th century, the importance of the RLEA declined alongside the decline in the railroad industry itself. As its member unions either merged into single entities or disaffiliated from the RLEA its influence waned, as did the number of its members. The RLEA attempted to counter this decline with the purchase of a railroad at least three different times in the 1970s and 1980s, though they were ultimately unsuccessful in this venture. Ongoing internal battles between the remaining chief executives of the railroad unions further weakened the RLEA until in 1997 it disbanded, handing over its responsibilities to the newly formed AFL-CIO Transportation Trades Department.
Scope and Contents
Inclusive date range: 1967-1972
Bulk dates: 1968-1972
This collection consists of the general and office files for the years 1968 through 1972. The order the files were kept in by the RLEA has been maintained in this collection.
The RLEA arranged their records chronologically by year in designated record groups. These record groups are used for each calendar year. Each record group consists of numerous files, the majority of which are maintained from year to year. Only when the executive council removed a particular issue from their monthly meeting agendas, records related to that issue were removed from the record group. The RLEA created "File Guides" for each year of record keeping. Those documents may be found in the collection to help researchers locate specific papers and may also be used to track what issues were continued and which were closed.
The record groups used by the RLEA are as follows:
1. Government
2. Judicial
3. RLEA
4. Railroads
5. Other Organizations
6. International Affairs
7. Commuter Problems
Additionally, for the year 1968, there is a record group called "Legislation" that has its own file guide, which may be found in the collection.
The Government Records Group includes files on the following: Railroad Retirement Board; Medicare; President's Committee on Physically Handicapped; Equal Employment Opportunity Commission (EEOC); Civil Rights Act; Federal Housing Administration; State Department; Pan American Railway Conference; Department of Transportation; Interstate Commerce Commission; National Transportation Safety Board; National Mediation Board; National Railroad Adjustment Board; Bureau of Labor Statistics; the creation of Amtrak; Federal Railroad Administration; Labor Department; and files for each of the three branches of government.
The 1968 Legislation Records Group includes files on the following: Interstate Commerce Act; Railroad Safety legislation; amendments to the Railroad Retirement and Insurance Acts; Railway Labor Act; moratoriums on railroad mergers; Department of Transportation appropriations; discontinuations of railroad passenger service; anti-labor legislation; crew consist legislation; Social Security Act; Interstate System regulations; amendments to the Urban Mass Transportation Act of 1964; and a file on endorsements for the 1968 elections.
The Judicial Records Group includes files on the following: United States vs. Jacksonville Terminal Co. in re civil rights violations; Penn Central bankruptcy; reorganizations of Boston and Maine, Lehigh Valley, Erie-Lackawanna, Reading Railroad, and Central of New Jersey; United States vs. Seaboard Coast Line in re civil rights violations; and a union shop dispute on the Louisville and Nashville. See also RLEA files labelled "Lawyer's Bills," which contain itemized lists of legal matters the RLEA was involved in according to the bills of their general counsel.
The RLEA Records Group includes files on the following: constitutions and by-laws; correspondence files for each of their member organizations; minutes from monthly meetings, agendas for the monthly meetings; planning documents for the monthly February meeting in Miami, Florida; information on general office matters; insurance plans; Wage and Rules Movements; reports from RLEA committees; bills; and files on various strikes occurring in the United States in different industries.
The Railroads Records Group includes files on the following: the Penn Central bankruptcy proceedings; correspondence files with industry groups that represent carriers; the hospital associations of carriers; and the merger between the Illinois Central and the Gulf, Mobile and Ohio.
The Other Organization Records Group includes files on the following: the AFL-CIO and its various departments; the National Association of Railroad Passengers (NARP); the United Nations; Labor newspaper; and various charitable organizations supported by the RLEA.
The International Affairs Records Group includes files on the following: exchange programs with railroaders from other countries; the Bureau of International Labor Affairs (ILAB); the International Labour Organization (ILO); and the International Transport Workers' Federation (ITWF) and its various departments.
The Commuter Problems Records Group includes files on the following: adequacies and discontinuances of intercity passenger trains; applications for federal grants by urban transit authorities including New York City and the New York metropolitan area, Chicago, the Bay Area, Washington DC, New Haven, and Philadelphia; and hearings before the ICC on route discontinuances.
Of particular interest in this collection are the files regarding the implementation of the Civil Rights Act and its amendments. The effects of this legislation on the transportation industry and in railroad labor organizations is evidenced by the prevalence of the topic in all of the above record groups. In the Government record groups, there are files relating to the implementation of the act and the proceedings regarding workplace discrimination before the federally appointed commissions. The RLEA record groups contain the reports of committees dedicated to civil rights and the EEOC. This group also contains correspondence from the Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters, a historically African- American union, regarding the racial discrimination present in other railroad labor organizations. Finally, the monthly meeting agendas and minutes include discussion of the various cases in which the RLEA's member organizations were sued along with the railroad carriers for racial discrimination. The case files and court filings for those cases are found in the Judicial record groups. The Other Organizations record group contains extensive documentation from the AFL-CIO's Civil Rights Department about how their affiliated groups should support the Civil Rights Act and how the groups should implement the provisions of the act. Finally, the Commuter Problems record group contains rich documentation of urban transportation system in major U.S. metropolitan areas and this includes the agreements between transit authorities and unions that are in compliance with the Civil Rights Act.
Also of interest in this collection is the clear change in federal policies during the transition from the Johnson administration to the Nixon administration in 1969. This includes the type of regulations and safety measures applied to the railroad industry, a marked increase in route discontinuances with a greater amount of support given to the Interstate Highway System, the removal of the labor-affiliated RLEA executive-secretary from the Pan American Railway Conference, the increase in "Right-to-Work" legislation, and major changes made to the Railroad Retirement Act and Unemployment Insurance benefits.
The 1969 RLEA Record Group contains correspondence from six member organizations withdrawing from the RLEA to create their own railroad labor organization, the Congress of Railway Unions. The six organizations who founded this group were the Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employes [BMoW], the Brotherhood of Railway, Airline, and Steamship Clerks, Freight Handlers, Express and Station Employes [BRAC], the United Transportation Union [UTU], Transit Workers' Union [TWU], Seafarers' International Union of North America [SIU], and the Hotel and Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union [HERE]. The RLEA and the Congress of Railway Unions worked together after their split to protect their members during the numerous mergers and bankruptcies that were impacting the industry at this time.
Finally, this collection contains extensive documentation of the Penn Central Transportation Company's bankruptcy proceedings. The records document the catastrophic effect this bankruptcy had on rail transportation in the Northeastern United States. The need for continued passenger and freight service was addressed by Congress, which created two federally subsidized carriers: Amtrak for passenger service, and Conrail for freight service. This collection contains extensive documentation of the legislation, negotiations, collective bargaining, and Congressional hearings that were involved in the creation of Amtrak.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: 5484: Railway Labor Executives' Association Records 5728: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records 5300: Railway Labor Executives' Association Miscellany 6087: Railway Labor Executives' Association Additional Records
Medicare; Discrimination in employment -- Law and legislation -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Railroads -- United States; Strikes and lockouts -- Vineyard laborers -- United States; Railroads -- Mergers -- United States; Bankruptcy -- United States; Railroad law -- United States; Local transit -- Law and legislation -- United States; Urban transportation -- Law and legislation -- United States; Arbitration, Industrial -- United States; Collective bargaining -- Railroads -- United States; Railroads -- United States -- Employees; Railroads -- Employees -- Labor unions; Railway Labor Executives Association; Travel insurance; AFL-CIO; American Railway Supervisors Association; American Train Dispatchers Association; Brotherhood of Locomotive Engineers (U.S.); Brotherhood of Locomotive Firemen and Enginemen; Brotherhood of Maintenance of Way Employees; Brotherhood of Railroad Signalmen; Brotherhood of Railroad Trainmen; Brotherhood Railway Carmen of America; Brotherhood of Railway Clerks; Brotherhood of Sleeping Car Porters; Hotel & Restaurant Employees and Bartenders International Union; International Association of Machinists and Aerospace Workers; International Brotherhood of Boilermakers, Iron Ship Builders, Blacksmiths, Forgers, and Helpers; International Brotherhood of Electrical Workers; International Brotherhood of Firemen and Oilers; International Organization of Masters, Mates, and Pilots; National Marine Engineers' Beneficial Association (U.S.); Order of Railway Conductors and Brakemen; Railroad Yardmasters of America; Railway Employes' Department, AFL-CIO; Sheet Metal Workers' International Association; Switchmen's Union of North America; Transportation Communications International Union; Seafarers' International Union of North America; United Transportation Union; United States. Railroad Retirement Board; United States. Railroad Unemployment Insurance Act; United States. Equal Employment Opportunity Commission; United States. Federal Housing Administration; United States. Deppartment of State; Congreso Panamericano de Ferrocarriles; United States. Department of Transportation; United States. National Transportation Safety Board; United States. Federal Railroad Administration; United States. Bureau of Labor; United States. Interstate Commerce Commission; United States. National Mediation Board; United States. National Railroad Adjustment Board; United States. President's Committee on Employment of the Physically Handicapped; Amtrak; United Farm Workers; Penn Central Transportation Company; Association of American Railroads; National Railway Labor Conference (U.S.); Southeastern Pennsylvania Transportation Authority; San Francisco Bay Area Rapid Transit District (Calif.); Port Authority of New York and New Jersey; Washington Metropolitan Area Transit Authority; Massachusetts Bay Transportation Authority; Chicago Transit Authority; New York (State). Metropolitan Transportation Authority; International Transport Workers' Federation; International Confederation of Free Trade Unions; United States. Office of High-Speed Ground Transportation; United States. Urban Mass Transportation Act of 1964; United States. Interstate Commerce Act; United States. Railroad Retirement Act; United States. Railroad Safety Legislation; United States. Railway Labor Act; United States. Social Security Act; United States. Civil Rights Act of 1964
5664255
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board. Reports., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  For FY 1967. Includes statistical tables for distribution.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board. Reports [folder 1 of 3], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2a)
  Amendments to increase benefits and Medicare.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board [folder 2 of 3], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2b)
  Includes information on benefits claims, compulsory retirement, analysis of employee contributions (taxes) and benefits, and survivor benefits. Also includes bulletins, statistical information, and mailers to member unions.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board [folder 3 of 3], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 2c)
  Information on how to file for retirement and apply for Medicare; lists of meetings with RLEA and member unions; bill to improve adequacy of widow's benefits; monthly benefit statistics; annuity charts; papers describing the program for new railroaders; and memo in re effect of Age Discrimination portion of Employment Act of 1967.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Membership and Staff Appointment, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Vacancies and Senate appointments.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Administrative Practices and Procedures, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Field Offices, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  No records contained in folder when collection accessioned.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Mechanization and Centralization of Claims Payments, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Duplicates of pamphlets in ffs. 2 and 3.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Coverage of Railroads and Unions as Employers, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7a)
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Status of Funds, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 7b)
  Actuarial notes in re Railroad Retirement Fund.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Railroad Retirement and Unemployment Insurance Systems, 1967-1968 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Includes pamphlet "Benefits for Railroad Workers and Their Families."
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Military Service Credits, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Educational Program, Meetings, Films, Etc., 1968 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Information in re RLEA's education outreach for changes to Railroad Retirement and Insurance Acts. Includes survey instrument to measure how effective information sessions are.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Press Releases, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  In re monthly benefit statistics and changes to Railroad Retirement and Insurance programs.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Supplemental Retirement Plans, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Correspondence with John Hiltz (NRLC) in re carriers' supplemental retirement programs for employees.
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, Safety Studies, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Government. Railroad Retirement Board, National Reporting Officers' Memoranda, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Reports from regional meetings in re RLEA data dissemination. Contains pamphlets from the Chicago Office of the Railroad Retirement Board.
- Government. Administration of Medicare, Financial Intermediary, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Pamphlet "A Brief Outline of Medical Insurance Benefits Under Medicare" and correspondence regarding its distribution.
- Government. U.S. Information Agency, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- Government. President's Committee on the Physically Handicapped, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Includes pamphlets "Performance: The Story of the Handicapped" and "Design for All Americans: A Report of the National Commission on Architectural Barriers to Rehabilitation of the Handicapped." Also a memo from the committee in re employing the developmentally disabled.
- Government. Civil Aeronautics Board, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18a)
- Government. Appointment of BRAC President to Equal Employment Opportunity Committee, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 18b)
  Joint venture of AAR and RLEA.
- Government. Equal Employment, Civil Rights Act [folder 1 of 2], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19a)
  Folder contains reports to RLEA in re implementation of Civil Rights Act, specifically the suits brought by Ramsey Clark, the Attorney Genera od the United States, against both carriers and against the RLEA and its member unions. Includes correspondence, articles about institutional racism of unions, an AFL-CIO pamphlet "Labor and Equal Rights," and filings in front of the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission.
- Government. Equal Employment, Civil Rights Act [folder 2 of 2], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 19b)
  Filings before the Equal Employment Opportunity Commission and District Courts by railroad employees against both carriers and unions.
- Government. Civil Rights Act [folder 1 of 2], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20a)
  Filings alleging discrimination again various carriers and railroad unions. Also includes Conciliation Agreements from the EEOC.
- Government. Civil Rights Act [folder 2 of 2], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 20b)
- Government. Railroad Committee on Equal Employment Opportunity, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Contains bilingual (English/Spanish) pamphlet distributed by UFW, "Right to Work Laws: A Trap for America's Minorities / El derecho a trabajar: una trampa para los minorias EE.UU." The pamphlet was written by Cesar Chavez and Bayard Rustin. Also contains EEOC filings, Conciliation Agreements, orders to a local unions to turn over their records to the EEOC, orders to file information on union apprenticeship programs, correspondence in re standard operating procedure for member unions to inform each other when they are sued for discrimination, information on age and sex discrimination, and a report from the AFL-CIO's Department of Civil Rights.
- Government. Peace Corps, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Government. President's Commission on the Status of Women, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Government. Freedom from Hunger Foundation, 1968 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  RLEA bought tickets to the gala from a senator's wife.
- Government. White House Conference, "To Fulfill These Rights?", 1968 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Pamphlet containing the speeches from this event.
- Government. Federal Housing Administration, Low Cost Housing [folder 1 of 2], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 26a)
  H.U.D. pamphlets on low-income housing, housing discrimination, and housing for the elderly and handicapped.
- Government. Federal Housing Administration, Low Income Housing [folder 2 of 2], 1968 (Box 1, Folder 26b)
  H.U.D. pamphlets on low income housing, housing discrimination, and housing for the elderly and handicapped.